KAREN JEFFREY

Centre for Medical Informatics, Usher Institute, The University of Edinburgh 07791 152 844 | karen.jeffrey@ed.ac.uk

SUMMARY

I am a Research Fellow in Medical Informatics, passionate about using data to improve health outcomes. I have advanced statistical and data science skills, and eight years' professional experience in research, leading project teams, fundraising, and stakeholder engagement.

EDUCATION

2017 - 2021	Ph.D., Political	Economy (Pass	with no corrections)	King's College London

- 2009 2010 M.Sc., Ecological Economics (Distinction) University of Edinburgh
- 2003 2007 B.A. (Hons.), Media (2:1) Queen Margaret University

EMPLOYMENT

2023 - present	Research Fellow, Medical Informatics University of Edinburgh
2022 - 2023	Postdoctoral Data Analyst, Medical Informatics University of Edinburgh
2021 - 2022	Senior Intelligence Analyst, Public Health NHS Lothian
2017 - 2018	Senior Research Consultant BBC Media Action (International development)
2013 - 2016	Researcher New Economics Foundation (Economic think tank)
2011 - 2013	Consultant Delta Energy and Environment (Energy consultancy)
2010 - 2011	Energy Advisor Energy Saving Trust/Changeworks (Charity)

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- 2024 Reproducibility Recognition, Health Data Research UK awarded to the EAVE II Team for commitment to transparency throughout the research lifecycle.
- Florence Nightingale Award, Royal Statistical Society awarded to the EAVE II Long COVID team for excellence in healthcare data analytics. (Role: Lead Analyst).

 Mary Somerville Medal, Royal Society of Edinburgh awarded to the EAVE II

 Team for exceptional achievement in teamwork and collaborative endeavour.

Postdoc Recognition Award, University of Edinburgh's College of Medicine & Veterinary Medicine for academic citizenship.

Press coverage of the EAVE II Long COVID study, including online, and interviews on TV (BBC) and radio (BBC Good Morning Scotland, BBC Radio 5 Live).

- 2017 GRE verbal reasoning & analytical writing at the 94th & 93rd percentile of test-takers.
- 2013-16 **Press coverage** of publications produced at the New Economics Foundation, including coverage by the BBC, Daily Mail, Financial Times, Herald, Independent, ITV, Observer, Telegraph, Forbes and international press in more than 30 countries worldwide.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Jeffrey, K**., Woolford, L., Maini, R., et al. (2024). Identifying long COVID using electronic health records: a national observational cohort study in Scotland. *eClinicalMedicine*. 71(102590).
- 2. **Jeffrey, K.** & Matakos, K. (2024). Automation anxiety, fairness perceptions, and redistribution: How past experience conditions the response to future job loss. *Journal of Economic Behavior & Organization*. 221, 174-190.
- 3. Shi, T., Millington, T., Robertson, C., **Jeffrey, K.**, et al. (2024). Risk of winter hospitalisation and death from acute respiratory infections in Scotland: national retrospective cohort study. *Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine*. (In press.)
- 4. Millington, T., Morrison, K., **Jeffrey, K.** et al. (2024). Caveats in reporting of national vaccine uptake. *Journal of Global Health.* 14(03006)
- 5. Amele, S., McCabe, R., Kibuchi, E., et al. (2024). Quality of ethnicity data within Scottish health records: the implications of misclassification for the observation of ethnic inequalities in severe COVID-19: A national linked data study. *Journal of Public Health.* 46(1).
- 6. Macdonald, C., Palmateer, N., McAuley, A., et al. (2024) Association between antibody response post-vaccination and severe COVID-19 outcomes: national population-based cohort study in Scotland. *npj Vaccines*. (In press.)
- 7. Kerr, S., Greenland, S., **Jeffrey, K.**, et al. (2023). Understanding and reporting odds ratios and rate ratios in case-control studies. *Journal of Global Health* 13(04101).
- 8. Morrison, K., Cullen, L., James, A., et al. (2023). Predictors of incomplete COVID-19 vaccine schedule among adults in Scotland: Two retrospective cohort analyses of the primary schedule and third dose. *Vaccine* 41(40), 5863-5876
- 9. Kerr, S., Millington, T., Rudan, I., et al. (2023). External validation of the QCovid 2 and 3 risk prediction algorithms for risk of COVID-19 hospitalisation and mortality in adults: a national cohort study in Scotland. *BMJ Open 13:e075958*.
- 10. **Jeffrey, K.** (2021). Automation and the future of work: how rhetoric shapes the response in policy preferences. *Journal of Economic Behavior & Organization 192, 417-433*.

UNDER REVIEW

- 1. **Jeffrey, K**., Hammersley, V., Maini, R., et al. Deriving and validating a risk prediction model for long COVID: population-based, retrospective cohort study in Scotland.
- 2. Shah, S.A., **Jeffrey, K.**, Robertson, C. and Sheikh, A. NHS Scotland's elective care backlog: national, regional, and speciality-based analysis and modelling to estimate capacity needs.

SELECTED THINK TANK PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Jeffrey, K.**, Abdallah, S. & Michaelson, J. (2017). The Cost of Loneliness to UK Employers. London: New Economics Foundation.
- 2. **Jeffrey, K.**, Wheatley, H. & Abdallah, S. (2016). The Happy Planet Index 2016: A Global Index of Sustainable Wellbeing. London: New Economics Foundation.
- 3. **Jeffrey, K.** and Michaelson, J. (2015). Five Headline Indicators of National Success: A Clearer Picture of How the UK is Performing. London: New Economics Foundation.
- 4. **Jeffrey, K.**, Mahony, S., Michaelson, J. and Abdallah, S. (2014). Well-being at Work: A Review of the Literature. London: New Economics Foundation.

INVITED TALKS AND CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2024	International Conference Royal Statistical Society
2023	Medical Informatics Seminar University of Edinburgh
2022	National Strategic Network for Long COVID NHS National Services Scotland
	Academic GPs Meeting on Long COVID University of Edinburgh
	Primary Care Practitioners' Session Public Health Scotland
2021	Political Science & Political Economy Seminar London School of Economics
2020	Political Behaviour Colloquium European University Institute
	Global Online Meeting Economic Science Association
	Early Career Network Conference Political Studies Association
	Early Career Researcher Seminar University of Southampton
	NORFACE TECHNO Group Norwegian University of Science and Technology
	Quantitative Political Economy Seminar King's College London
	Centre for Experimental Social Sciences Conference New York University
019	Centre for British Politics, PhD Conference King's Collge London
018	AI Safety and Policy Event Artificial Intelligence Strategy and Policy Network
016	Parliamentary Roundtable: How Should We Measure National Success? UK Governmentary
015	Five Headline Indicators of National Success: Report Launch Royal Statistical Society
2014	European Social Survey Policy Seminar OECD

TEACHING & SUPERVISION

2018-20	Teaching Assistant The Political Economy of Inequality, King's College London
2018-19	Teaching Assistant Microeconomics 1, King's College London
2016	Volunteer GCSE Maths Tutor Action Tutoring
2015-16	Masters Supervision for MSc in Ecological Economics, University of Edinburgh,

GRANTS, FELLOWSHIPS & FUNDRAISING

2024	Usher Institute Small Grant University of Edinburgh (£650)
2022	Data Skills for Work The Data Lab (£300)
2020	London Interdisciplinary Social Sciences Scholarship ESRC (£9,000)
	Small Academic Expenses Grant Royal Economic Society (£450)
	Post-Graduate Research Bursary Grants King's College London (£1,000)
2019	Post-Graduate Research Bursary Grants King's College London (£500)
	Cohort Activity Grant ESRC (£1,600)
2018	Research Development Fund King's College London (£2,000)
2017	$\textbf{London Interdisciplinary Social Sciences Doctoral Scholarship} \ ESRC \ (\pounds 68,000)$
	Bentham PhD Fellowship University College London (£64,000, declined)
2011-16	Contributed to successful tenders for funding from European Commission, E.On,
	British Gas, Vattenfall, Bosch, Vaillant, DECC, Co-op, & Kingfisher Group.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

2023-present	Impact Committee Usher Institute, University of Edinburgh
2021-present	Reviewer BMJ Open; Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics; European
	Journal of Political Economy; European Economic Review.
2021-2023	Journal Club Organiser Medical Informatics Group, University of Edinburgh.
2018	Conference Organiser and Chair AI and Automation: Implications for
	researchers in the social sciences. One-day conference hosted at King's College London.
2018-20	Reading Group Organiser Formal Theory Group, King's College London.
2016	Event Organiser and Chair An evening in conversation with Ed Miliband MP
	and Nick Srnicek. The Future of Work: Harnessing new technologies to benefit all.
2014-16	Secretariat for the All-Party Parliamentary Group on Wellbeing Economics.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

2024-present	Office for National Statistics Accredited Researcher
2021-present	European Association of Labour Economists
2020-21	Royal Economic Society
	American Economic Association
	Economic Science Association
2011-14	Institute for Environmental Management and Assessment (Associate Member)
2010-11	International Society for Ecological Economics

TRAINING

2024	Research, GDPR and Confidentiality (renewal) Medical Research Council
	Safe Researcher Training UK Data Service
	Data Science for Domain Scientists Data Science Unit, University of Edinburgh
2023	Aspiring Manager Program University of Edinburgh
	Data Science in Stratified Healthcare & Precision Medicine University of Edinburgh
2022	Machine Learning with Python ED-DaSH, University of Edinburgh
	High-Dimensional Statistics in R ED-DaSH, University of Edinburgh
	GIT for Me: Introduction to GitHub Jumping Rivers
2021	Managing Difficult Conversations NHS Professionals
2018	Introduction to R for Biostatistics and Health Informatics King's College London
	PhD Summer School: Applied Microeconomics University of Lancaster
2017	Principles of Economics with Calculus (MOOC) California Institute of Technology
	Calculus 1a and Calculus 1b (MOOC) Massachusetts Institute of Technology
2014	Introduction to Statistics Using SPSS Imperial College London
2013	Statistics: Making Sense of Data (MOOC) University of Toronto

Introduction to Computer Science and Programming in Python (MOOC) MIT

SOFTWARE SKILLS

R, LATEX, Qualtrics, SPSS, Microsoft Office

REFEREES

Prof. Sir Aziz Sheikh

Professor of Primary Care Research and Development, Director of Usher Institute Usher Institute, University of Edinburgh aziz.sheikh@ed.ac.uk

Dr. Philip Conaglen

Lead Consultant in Public Health
Directorate of Public Health and Health Protection, NHS Lothian
philip.conaglen@nhslothian.scot.nhs.uk

Prof. Konstantinos Matakos

Professor of Economics

Department of Political Economy, King's College London konstantinos.matakos@kcl.ac.uk